A Finding Aid to the Samuel F. B. Morse Papers, 1826-2009, bulk 1826-1871, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Samuel F. B. Morse papers
1826-2009
bulk 1826-1871
Archives of American Art
Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872
AAA.morsesam
Archival Resource Key
0.4 Linear feet
The papers of painter and inventor Samuel F. B. Morse date from 1826-2009 (bulk 1826-1871), and measure 0.4 linear feet. This small collection documents Morse's role in the early years of the National Academy of Design through his correspondence as the academy's first president, and also includes scattered biographical material, Morse's writings and notes on art from that period, printed material including clippings about Morse and an exhibition catalog, eight photographs, including one of Morse, and a microfilm reel of one of Morse's sketchbooks.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter and inventor Samuel F. B. Morse date from 1826-2009 (bulk 1826-1871), and measure 0.4 linear feet. This small collection documents Morse's role in the early years of the National Academy of Design through his correspondence as the academy's first president, and also includes scattered biographical material, Morse's writings and notes on art from that period, printed material including clippings about Morse and an exhibition catalog, eight photographs, including one of Morse, and a microfilm reel of one of Morse's sketchbooks.
Arrangement
Due to its small size the collection is arranged as one series.
Series 1: Samuel F. B. Morse Papers, 1826-2009 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2019 and is available on the Archives of American Art website. Materials which have not been digitized include blank pages, blank versos of photographs, duplicates, and the microfilm reel. Morse's published book has had only the cover, title pages, and table of contents pages digitized.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by the National Academy of Design in 2018.
Biographical / Historical
Portrait painter and inventor Samuel Finley Breese Morse (1791-1872), was a founding member of the National Academy of Design who was subsequently known for his invention of the Morse code.
Morse was born in Massachusetts and educated at Yale College. In 1811 he traveled to England and was admitted to the Royal Academy. He returned to the United States in 1815 and began a career as a painter, primarily of portraits.
From 1826-1845 he served as president of the newly founded National Academy of Design in New York City. In the 1830s Morse developed the concept of a single-wire telegraph and the Morse code, and was involved in the growth of the commercial use of telegraphy throughout the world. Morse was also known for his portraits of the Marquis de Lafayette, and presidents John Adams and James Monroe.
Related Materials
The bulk of Samuel F. B. Morse's papers are held by the Library of Congress.
- Samuel F. B. Morse Papers, 1826-2009; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet
  Arrangement
  Records are arranged by type.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Materials which have not been digitized include blank pages, blank versos of photographs, duplicates, and the microfilm reel. Morse's published book has had only the cover, title pages, and table of contents pages digitized.
  Scope and Contents
  Morse's biographical material records the $1000 gift to the National Academy of Design bequeathed in his will. Morse's correspondence as president of the academy details the conflicts with the American Academy of Fine Arts, and failed attempts to bring about a union of the two organizations. It also documents other academy business such as exhibitions and interactions with other arts institutions, as well as Morse's independent work as an artist receiving commissions. This correspondence is described in two itemized lists compiled by National Academy of Design staff members which are included in this series. Additional correspondence documents negotiations with Morse's son, Edward L. Morse, to secure the gift of the Morse papers that constitute this collection.
  Morse's writings and notes on art, primarily in the form of lectures and lecture notes, can also be found here. They include his "Discourse" on the National Academy of Design delivered on the academy's one year anniversary, a criticism of that address, and Morse's response to the criticism. Some of the loose notes were assigned an alphanumeric identification system that does not appear to be explained in the collection, but has been left as is.
  Printed material includes eleven articles about Morse, one 1871 edition of the publication Dots and Dashes, by the Morse Telegraph club, Inc., an obituary for Morse's granddaughter, Clara, and a catalog for the exhibition Samuel F. B. Morse: Paintings, Inventions, Documents (1956) at the Syracuse Museum of Art. Also found is a copy of Morse's 1835 book Foreign Conspiracy Against the Liberties of the United States.
  Photographs include a copy print of a photo of Morse taken at fifty-nine years of age, shortly after he sent his first successful telegram between Washington and Baltimore on May 24, 1844; three photographs taken at the April 1968 dedication of a plaque by members of the Morse Telegraph Club; a photo of a tablet on Morse's house; and a photograph of a man, probably Morse's son, William Goodrich Morse. Also found is a photo of a charcoal sketch by Morse of his niece, entitled "Lottie," and a photo of a sketch of an unidentified woman, by Kalman Oswald.
  - Biographical Material, Morse Family Trees, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Material, Morse's Gift to National Academy of Design, 1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1826-1868, Itemized List, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1826-1829; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1830-1836; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1842-1868, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence circa 1826-1833, Itemized List, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, circa 1826-1833, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correpondence, National Academy of Design, 1932-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, National Academy of Design and Edward L. Morse, circa 1909-1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings and Notes, Archival Resource Key
    - Article, Criticism of Morse's "Discourse", 1827; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Article, Morse's Reply to Criticism of His "Discourse", 1828; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lectures, "A Discourse Delivered on Thursday, May 3, 1827…Before the National Academy of Design", Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lectures, "On the Affinity of Painting with the Other Fine Arts", Archival Resource Key
      - Lecture 1, circa 1826-1833, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Lecture 2, 1826; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Lecture 2, Alternate Opening, 1826; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Lecture 3, 1826; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Lecture 4, 1826; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Notes, circa 1826-1833, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lectures, Principles of Fine Art, circa 1835; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Lecture Notes, Bound Volume 1, circa 1820s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Lecture Notes, Bound Volume 2, circa 1820s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lecture Notes, A: 1-17, circa 1820s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Lecture Notes, B: 18-33, circa 1820s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Lecture Notes, C: 34-54, circa 1820s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lecture Notes, A-H, circa 1820s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Notes on National Academy of Design, circa 1820s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Printed Material, circa 1851-1871; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, 1872-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material, Foreign Conspiracy Against the Liberties of the United States by Morse, 1835; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Artwork, Unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1922-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Microfilm Reel of Morse Sketchbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)